<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The holy salutation of the blessed Apostle Saint Jude to the saints and seruants of God. Preached at Pauls Crosse the seuenteenth of Nouember. Anno. Dom. 1611. By Francis Tomlinson, preacher of the Word, and chaplaine to the right honourable, the Lord Ellesmere, Lord High Chancellor of England, and Chancellor of Oxford.</title>
            <author>Tomlinson, Francis.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1612</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 91 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 30 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A13810</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 24111</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S106618</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99842331</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99842331</idno>
            <idno type="VID">6976</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A13810)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 6976)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 583:10)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The holy salutation of the blessed Apostle Saint Jude to the saints and seruants of God. Preached at Pauls Crosse the seuenteenth of Nouember. Anno. Dom. 1611. By Francis Tomlinson, preacher of the Word, and chaplaine to the right honourable, the Lord Ellesmere, Lord High Chancellor of England, and Chancellor of Oxford.</title>
                  <author>Tomlinson, Francis.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 51, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Imprinted by Felix Kyngston for George Norton, dwelling neare Temple barre,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>At London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1612.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Folger Shakespeare Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:6976:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE HOLY SALV<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TATION OF THE BLESSED APOSTLE Saint <hi>Jude,</hi> to the Saints <hi>and ſeruants of God.</hi> PREACHED AT PAVLS Croſſe the ſeuenteenth of Nouem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber. <hi>Anno Dom.</hi> 1611. By FRANCIS TOMLINSON, Preacher of the Word, and Chaplaine to the Right Honourable, the Lord <hi>Elleſmere,</hi> Lord <hi>High Chancellor of England, and</hi> Chancellor of Oxford.</p>
            <q>Quibus parum vel quibus nimium mihi ignoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cant; quibus autem ſatis eſt, non mihi ſed domino mecum gratias agant.</q>
            <p>
               <hi>AT LONDON</hi> Imprinted by FELIX KYNGSTON for <hi>George Norton, dwelling neare Temple</hi> barre. 1612.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:6976:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:6976:2"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT WORSHIPFVLL, RELI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>GIOVS, AND VERTV<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Knight, Sir THOMAS LVCIE, <hi>high Sheriffe of Warwick-ſhire, mercy, peace, and loue bee</hi> multiplied.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>Ight Worſhipfull, when I was cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led by my Lord of London to preach at Pauls Croſſe, I reſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued with my ſelfe to anſwere with <hi>Moſes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Exod. 5.10.</note> I am not eloquent but ſlow of ſpeech, ſlow of tongue; with <hi>Ieremie,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ier. 1.6.</note> I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ſpeake for I am a child in vnderſtanding; with <hi>Iohn Baptiſt, non ſum dignus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Matth. 3.11.</note> I am not worthie; and with Saint <hi>Paul,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Cor. 15.9.</note> I am the leaſt of the Apoſtles, not worthy to bee called an Apoſtle; neuertheleſſe being commanded I did obey, obeying ſpake, ſpeaking, feared rather a reprouing then an approuing of that I ſpake; howbeit (beyond all deſert and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire)
<pb facs="tcp:6976:3"/> it pleaſed ſome of friendſhip and affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction to commend, others of fauour and good conceit euen then conceiued, inſtantly to vrge that my poore paines might be printed, which I vtterly refuſed as vnworthy to ſee the light; ſince I vnderſtand by ſome, that ſome haue giuen out, that if I will not giue a true and perfect copie, they will put it out in parts, peeces, and imperfect as they tooke it: of two euils therefore I haue choſen the leſſe, chuſing rather to vndergo the hard cenſures of ſuch, as are more readie to cenſure others then doe any good themſelues, then to ſuffer this ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple Sermon without my knowledge and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent to be thrust forth in imperfect notes. I affect not popular praiſe, <hi>nam quis ego ſum, aut quae eſt in me facultas?</hi> Neither doe I reſpect the vncharitable cenſures of Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uſten.</note> Atheiſts, Schiſmatickes; for, <hi>qui vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lens detrahit famae meae, nolens addit mercedi meae:</hi> He which with his will im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paires my name, againſt his will augments my reward. But my deſire is onely that my poore talent may bee imployed to Gods glory; let God be glorified by me, and let me ſtill bee vilified for Gods ſake. <hi>Not vnto mee O Lord, not vnto mee, but to thy holy
<pb facs="tcp:6976:3"/> name giue the glory.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That I am bold to ſhroud theſe firſt fruits of my ſimple labours vnder your Right Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipfull patronage (beſides priuate cauſes) your Zeale of Gods glory, delight in Gods ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred word, great loue to learning and religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, good fauours towards Gods Miniſters haue deſeruedly inuited mee; <hi>macte virtute eſto:</hi> goe forward I beſeech you in godlines, encreaſe in grace, grow from ſtrength to ſtrength, from vertue to vertue, be conſtant in the faith, ſtoutly defend the truth, earneſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly contend for the truth, let not the cunning Papiſt ſeduce you, nor the malecontent Schiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maticke inſinuate himſelfe into you, nor the godleſſe Atheiſt ring and ſing in your eares diuelliſh charmes; but honour him ſincerely which will honour you, loue him feruent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly which loueth you, delight in him chief<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly which delighteth in you, cleaue to him inſeparably which will neuer forſake you: <hi>ſed quid verbis opus, vbi nihil opus?</hi> I know you doe it,<note place="margin">Phil. 1.3.4.5</note> and I thanke my God hauing you in perfect memorie alwaies in all my prayers, praying with gladneſſe becauſe of the fellow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip which you haue in the Goſpell, from the firſt day I knew you till now; yet as <hi>Paul, Syl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uanus,</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:6976:4"/> and <hi>Timotheus</hi> gaue hearty thanks to God for the Theſſalonians, that they had receiued the Goſpell, in ſuch ſort that they were examples not onely to them of Macedo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia and Achaia,<note place="margin">1. Theſ. 1.2.7.</note> but alſo to the Chriſtians in all quarters; ſo doe they earneſtly deſire them to continue according to their good begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings;<note place="margin">cap. 4.1.</note> we beſeech you brethren (ſay they) and exhort you in the Lord Ieſus that ye encreaſe more and more, as ye haue receiued of vs, how ye ought to walk &amp; pleaſe God; as if they ſhuld haue ſaid, we do not command you as Lords o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer you (as now the Pope doth) <hi>ſic volo ſic iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iubeo, ſtat pro ratione volu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tas;</hi> &amp; as <hi>Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantius</hi> that Arian Emperour, <hi>quod ego volopro canone ſit;</hi> but we beſeech, entreat and exhort you by the Lord Ieſus, that if you reſpect and reuerence Christ, if you feare him as a Lord, and loue him as Ieſus, ſuffer the words of exhortation; for wee ſpeake from him and for him: In like maner I beſeech you (Right worſhipfull) giue me leaue, <hi>currenti addere calcar;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Seneca.</note> 
               <hi>habet hoc proprium ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neroſus animus vt excitetur ad honeſta;</hi> It is proper to a noble minde to bee excited to honeſt actions; and ſeeing I know that you know <hi>in religione vera virtus, in virtute
<pb facs="tcp:6976:4"/> vera nobilitas;</hi> and that <hi>nulla vera religio ſine ſapientia,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Lactantius.</note> 
               <hi>nec vlla vera ſapientia fine religione.</hi> Pardon my Zealous affection and tender care of your euerlasting good, enforce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing mee to beſeech you to goe forward in good things, and encreaſe more and more in godlineſſe, for declining in religion brings a ſtaine of honour, and a decay euen of tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall portion: I feare it not in you; for as it is no ſmall comfort to mee often to call to mind the tractableneſſe, willingneſſe, readineſſe, I found in you to drink in thirſtingly the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples of religion, when I taught you alſo the rudiments of Grammar; ſo is it, and euer ſhall be my great comfort, not onely to heare of it, but often to be an eye and eare witneſſe of your zeale for the truth of God, I meane your reſolute conſtancy, and conſtant reſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to defend the truth againſt malicious Papiſts, malecontent Schiſmaticks, and miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creant Atheiſts: continue in the ſame, fight the good fight, ſtir vp that gift of God which is in you, be faithfull vnto the end, and in the end you ſhall receiue the end of your faith e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen the ſaluation of your ſoule: In the meane time I humbly beſeech you to pardon my im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunate boldneſſe, and accept of this poore
<pb facs="tcp:6976:5"/> widdowes mite, as an vndoubted testimonie of my vnfained affection towards you in the Lord.</p>
            <p>Now the Lord of Lords enlarge his mercies more and more towards you, perpetuate to you an honourable name and memory a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongst his faithfull ſeruants in this preſent life, and crowne you with an endleſſe crowne of glory in the life to come.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your worſhips in all du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifull affection, <hi>FRANCIS TOMLINSON.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:6976:5"/>
            <head>THE HOLY SALVTATION OF the bleſſed Apoſtle <hi>S. Iude.</hi>
            </head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>IVDE 1.2.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p n="1">
                     <hi>1</hi> Iude a ſeruant of Ieſus Christ, and brother of Iames, to them that are called and ſanctified of God the Father, and reſerued to Ieſus Christ:</p>
                  <p n="2">
                     <hi>2</hi> Mercie vnto you, and peace and loue be multiplied.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His holy Epiſtle of the bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Apoſtle <hi>Iude,</hi> though ſhorte, yet ſententious; though little yet not light<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie to be regarded, for al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beit it containe not argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and matters of ſundrie ſorts, as the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred Epiſtles of other Apoſtles do, yet as it were in one generall exhortation, the Apoſtle exhorteth the Saints and ſeruants of God to conſtancie and perſeuerance in their profeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Goſpell; inueighing ſharply againſt
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:6976:6"/> carnall profeſſion and groſſe abuſing of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian religion: and alſo admoniſheth them to beware of impoſtors, ſeducers, falſe teachers, cunning deceauers, which were craftily crept in amongſt them, drawing men from puritie of religion to impuritie of the fleſh, whom the Apoſtle liuelie painteth out in their ſeue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall colours, and againſt whom he iuſtly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounceth the fearefull iudgements of God to be inflicted vpon them; for plaine and euident demonſtration whereof he ſetteth down ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifold examples and manifeſt teſtimonies out of the ſacred ſcriptures. The maine ſcope then, and generall drift of th'Apoſtle, in this Epiſtle is, partly to ſet downe the dutie of euery Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian, and partly to ſet out the corruptions of thoſe and theſe times. The occaſion of wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting this Epiſtle was this; It is affirmed by the moſt learned of all times, and agreed vpon by the beſt writers, that this Apoſtle <hi>Iude</hi> out-li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued many (yea moſt) of the Apoſtles; continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and preaching in <hi>Meſopotamia, Pontus, Perſis</hi> and other parts of the world, till the reigne of <hi>Domitian</hi> the Emperor, in whoſe reigne iniquitie reigned, impietie abounded, corruption of manners and diſſolution of life raged in euery place; Yea euen ſome which made an outward ſhew of religion waxed wanton, abuſing the free fauour grace and mercy of God promiſed and publiſhed in the Goſpell. Which when this holy man of God
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:6976:6"/> ſaw, (and ſeeing greeued at it) he wrote this Epiſtle, admoniſhing the Saintes of God to take heede to themſelues, leſt they alſo ſhould be carried away with the errors of the wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and ſo fall from their owne ſtedfaſtnes, and not onely ſo, but that in ſo dangerous times they ſhould earneſtlie contend againſt ſedu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers, and conſtantly defend the faith, truth, and religion of Ieſus Chriſt once receaued. Theſe words are the holy and religious ſalu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of the bleſſed Apoſtle S. <hi>Iude,</hi> wherein, (as vſually in euery ſalutation) it may pleaſe you to obſerue</p>
            <p>three circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances
<list>
                  <item>1. The perſon ſaluting.</item>
                  <item>2. The perſons ſaluted.</item>
                  <item>3. The forme or manner of ſalutation.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>The perſon ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luting, is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed three wayes
<list>
                  <item>1. By his name: <hi>Iude.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2. By his calling: <hi>A ſeruant of Ieſus Chriſt.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>3. By his kinred: <hi>The brother of Iames.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>The perſons ſalu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted are ador<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned and beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tified with 3. excellent ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tles.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. They are called of God.</item>
               <item>2. They are ſanctified by God.</item>
               <item>3. They are reſerued to Ieſus Chriſt.</item>
            </list>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:6976:7"/>
            <p>The forme of ſalutation is a prayer; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the Apoſtle</p>
            <p>wiſheth three bleſſing
<list>
                  <item>1. Mercie.</item>
                  <item>2. Peace.</item>
                  <item>3. Loue.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>Mercy, the fountaine of Saluation.</p>
            <p>Peace, the fruit of Mercy.</p>
            <p>Loue, the fruit of peace.</p>
            <p>Of theſe in order, by Gods aſſiſtance, and your chriſtian patience.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note>
               <hi>Iude,</hi> or <hi>Iudas:</hi> of this name our Sauiour had two Apoſtles; the one called <hi>Iudas Iſca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riot,</hi> who for thirtie peeces of ſiluer betrayed and baſely ſold his Lord and Maſter. <hi>Seruus Dominum, Diſcipulus magiſtrum, homo Deum, creatura creatorem tradidit, vendidit, viliſſimè vendidit:</hi> The ſeruant betrayed, ſold, moſt baſely ſold his Lord, the Diſciple his Maſter, man God, the creature the Creator. <hi>Infoelix mercator Iudas;</hi> Oh vnhappie, wretched, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curſed merchant <hi>Iudas.</hi> The other called <hi>Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>das,</hi> the ſonne of <hi>Alphaeus,</hi> called alſo <hi>Thad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daeus</hi> and <hi>Lebbaeus,</hi> which variety of names was giuen him (as ſome thinke) not onely to diſtinguiſh him from <hi>Iudas</hi> the traitor, but that the very name of <hi>Iudas,</hi> as odious to all, might vtterly be forgotten; howbeit this A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle not aſhamed of this and his name, in the very forefront of his Epiſtle calleth him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe <hi>Iudas:</hi> I rather thinke then that theſe names, <hi>Thaddaeus</hi> and <hi>Lebbaeus</hi> were giuen
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:6976:7"/> vnto this Apoſtle neither to diſtinguiſh him from <hi>Iudas</hi> the traitor, nor vtterly to extin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh the name of <hi>Iudas;</hi> but becauſe <hi>Iudas, Thaddaeus,</hi> and <hi>Lebbaeus</hi> ſignifie all one thing, to wit, praiſing or confeſſing. The occaſion of which name with the reaſon thereof is ſet downe in the 29. chapter of Geneſis the 35. verſe: For when <hi>Leah</hi> had borne three ſons to <hi>Iacob,</hi> ſhe conceiued and bare a fourth ſonne, ſaying; Now will I praiſe or confeſſe the Lord, and ſhe called his name <hi>Iudah.</hi> The au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor then of this Epiſtle could not bee <hi>Iudas</hi> the traitor, for hee had hanged himſelfe long before,<note place="margin">Euſeb. lib. <hi>4.</hi> cap. <hi>5.</hi>
               </note> nor <hi>Iude</hi> the fifteenth Biſhop of Ieru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem, for he was long after; but <hi>Iude</hi> the ſon of <hi>Alphaeus,</hi> and ſeruant of <hi>Ieſus Christ.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Serui à ſeruando;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Auguſtine, de ciuitate Dei, lib. <hi>19.</hi> cap. <hi>15.</hi>
               </note> becauſe ſuch as by right of warre and law of Armes might haue been ſlaine and put to death, being reſerued and kept aliue by the Emperours and conquerors were ſold and made ſeruants.</p>
            <p>Of ſeruants there are three ſorts.
<list>
                  <item>1. ſome by ſlauiſh voluntarie ſubiection.</item>
                  <item>2. ſome by condition.</item>
                  <item>3. ſome by profeſſion.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>The firſt, the ſeruants of ſinne, the ſecond of men, the third of God. The firſt ſeruice, ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, the ſecond ciuill, the third Chriſtian.</p>
            <p>Seruants of ſinne they are which with gree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dineſſe commit ſinne.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>1</hi> Facere pecca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum non eſt ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliciter peccare, ſed toto anima in peccatum in cumbere.</note> 
               <hi>Qui facit peccatum ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus eſt peccati:</hi> Hee which committeth ſinne
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:6976:8"/> (ſaith our Sauiour) he is the ſeruant of ſinne. Ioh. 8.34. That is, <hi>Quiſquis indulget peccatis, ſecure peccat, peccata peccatis addit, non potest non peccare.</hi> Whoſoeuer doth giue himſelfe o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer to commit ſinne with greedineſſe, doth ſinne with ſecurity, without remorſe, doth adde ſinnes vnto ſinnes without repentance; cannot but ſinne, hee is rightly tearmed the ſeruant of ſinne. Know yee not ſaith the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle, that to whomſoeuer yee giue your ſelues as ſeruants to obey,<note place="margin">Rom. 6.16.</note> his ſeruants yee are to whom yee obey, whether it bee of ſinne vnto death, or of obedience vnto righteouſneſſe? <hi>Duram ſeruiunt ſeruitutem:</hi> They which ſerue ſinne ſerue a hard ſeruice. <hi>Stipendium peccati mors;</hi> The wages of ſinne is death: <hi>Faciunt peccatum</hi> (ſaith <hi>Auguſtine) vt aliquam corpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ralem capere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t voluptatem;</hi>
               <note place="margin">In euangel. Iohannis tract. <hi>41.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>voluptas tranſit, pec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>catum manet; praeterit quod delectabat, remanet quod pungat.</hi> They commit ſinne, that by ſin they may take ſome corporall pleaſure; the pleaſure paſſeth away,<note place="margin">Nocet empta dolore voluptas.</note> the ſinne remaineth. That which once delighted is gone, that which may ſtill ſting abideth.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Seruants by condition they are, which are either borne ſuch by nature, or taken captiues in warre, or bought with money (they which are hired are hirelings) to ſuch ſeruants Saint <hi>Paule</hi> giueth graue counſell: Seruants o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bey thoſe,<note place="margin">Epheſ. 6.5.6.</note> which are your Maſters according to the fleſh with feare, trembling and ſimpli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citie
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:6976:8"/> of heart, not with eye ſeruice as men pleaſers, but as the ſeruants of Chriſt. <hi>Nomen iſtud culpa meruit, non natura.</hi>
               <note place="margin">De ciuitate Dei. lib. <hi>19.</hi> cap. <hi>15.</hi>
               </note> This name of ſeruant (ſaith S. <hi>Auguſtine</hi>) not nature but ſin deſerued: for the name of ſeruant was neuer heard of, till <hi>Noah</hi> curſed <hi>Canaan</hi> the ſonne of <hi>Cham</hi> who diſcouered his fathers nakednes.<note place="margin">Geneſ 9.25.</note> 
               <hi>Curſed bee Canaan a ſeruant of ſeruants ſhall he be.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Hence it may bee that the Pope is ſtiled <hi>Seruus ſeruorum</hi> a ſeruant of ſeruants, for he is a ſeruant of ſeruants, that ſerueth not Chriſt.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Seruants by office, calling and profeſſion they are, which being called, obey and offer their ſeruice to God and to his ſonne Chriſt <hi>Ieſus;</hi> theſe are of two ſortes; for men are ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the ſeruants of God generally or particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly; generally they are all the ſeruants of God which acknowledge him for their Lord, dedicate themſelues wholly to his ſeruice, endeuour to doe his will, and for his ſake pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiently, yea gladly ſuffer afflictions,<note place="margin">Iames 1.2.</note> perſecuti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, croſſes, loſſes, deriſions, death it ſelfe; <hi>hi veri ſerui veri Dei:</hi> theſe are true ſeruants of the true God; Such ſeruants bond and free, male and female, rich and poore, noble and ignoble, learned and vnlearned, Prince and people muſt be and will be, if they will be ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued: particularly and ſpecially they are the ſeruants of God, and of Chriſt, who in ſome ſeuerall and chiefe calling do ſeruice to God,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:6976:9"/> aduance his glorie; promote Chriſts king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome; Thus magiſtrates ſupreme and ſubor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinate in common wealthes, thus Arſhbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops, Biſhops, miniſters of the word <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> in a ſpecial ſeruice are the ſeruants of God &amp; of <hi>Ieſus</hi> Chriſt; both theſe latter wayes as wel by condition as by vocation, the Apoſtle <hi>Iude</hi> profeſſeth himſelfe the ſeruant of <hi>Ieſus Chriſt;</hi> by condition, becauſe by Chriſt he was freed, redeemed and deliuered from the ſlauerie of ſinne and tyrannie of Satan; by office and cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling becauſe not only in his generall calling, but chieflie in his particular, the Apoſtleſhip, he carefully and faithfully performed his ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice, to his Lord and Maſter <hi>Ieſus Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> The third thing to bee conſidered in this Apoſtle is his alliance or kinred, the brother of <hi>Iames;</hi> not the brother of <hi>Iames</hi> the ſonne of <hi>Zebedaeus</hi> and brother of <hi>Iohn,</hi> which <hi>Iames</hi> was killed by <hi>Herod;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Acts 12.2.</note> but the brother of <hi>Iames</hi> the ſonne of <hi>Alphaeus and Mary Claephas,</hi> the ſiſter of the bleſſed Virgin <hi>Mary,</hi> and ſo the coſen german of <hi>Ieſus Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>He calleth himſelfe the brother of <hi>Iames</hi> for two reſpects, the one to diſtinguiſh him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe from <hi>Iudas Iſcariot</hi> the ſonne of <hi>Simon,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iohn 6.70.</note> whom our Sauiour calleth a deuill, <hi>Nonne vos duodecim elegi?</hi> Haue I not choſen you twelue, and one of you is a deuill? the other to winne more credite (not to his perſon) but to his doctrine, that all men might know that
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:6976:9"/> this Epiſtle was penned, not by <hi>Iudas</hi> the trai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor, but by <hi>Iudas</hi> the brother of <hi>Iames</hi> the iuſt,<note place="margin">Dictum clari hominis facile admittitur.</note> and therefore might more reuerently receaue it, and more religiouſly regard it. Thus much for explication; now to application.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Firſt whereas the name of <hi>Iudas</hi> was giuen to <hi>Iſcariot</hi> the traitor, as wel as this holy Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle <hi>Thaddaeus,</hi> both hauing a like outward calling; both a like office, both Apoſtles of <hi>Ieſus Chriſt;</hi> yet this man good and godlie, that wicked and vngodly; Wee clearely ſee that it is not the name, title, or office that makes a good man; but the grace and mercy of God;<note place="margin">Iob. 32.9.</note> for as the learnedſt clarks haue not alwayes bin the wiſeſt men, ſo the greateſt in place either in Church or Common wealth, haue not alwayes bin the beſt men: If out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward titles and high places,<note place="margin">Freno indorato non fà megliora il cauallo.</note> could make men vertuous, religious, holy, godly, the ſeruants of <hi>Ieſus Chriſt. Iudas Iſcariot</hi> might haue bin as good, godly, holy as this Apoſtle, yea be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore him, for <hi>Iſcariot</hi> was Chriſts ſteward, his purſebearer, disburſer of all things for Chriſt and his companie, and yet behold, a thiefe, a traytor, a deuill: the like may be ſaid of <hi>Saule, Ahab, Ieroboam, Rehoboam, Abſolon, Achi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tophel. Haman, Herod:</hi> what need we go ſo farre for examples? <hi>Dominobis iſta naſcuntur;</hi> we haue plenty of theſe neare home; paſſing ouer ſome which haue bin Kings, Counſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lors, Archbiſhops, Biſhops, Iudges, Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:6976:10"/> Miniſters of the word in this land: I paſſe to <hi>Rome,</hi> and demand whether high places (the higheſt on earth as papiſts affirme) hath made Pope <hi>Silueſter</hi> the ſecond, a ſorce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer, negromancer, <hi>magus diabolicus,</hi> a deui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh magitian, one that gaue himſelfe to the deuill; Pope <hi>Alexander</hi> the ſixth, a moſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>digious filthie fellow, <hi>cuius auaritiae totus non ſufficit orbis; cuius luxuriae meretrix non ſufficit omnis;</hi> whoſe couetouſneſſe a whole world could not ſatisfie, whoſe filthineſſe all the whores in the world could not ſatisfie; Pope <hi>Hildebrand reipub: et eccleſiae peſtis &amp; perturba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor,</hi> the very plague and diſturber of Church and common wealth, good, godly, holy men; yet the Pope cannot erre either in life or doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine; Chriſt hath prayed for <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>Peters</hi> ſucceſſors, that their faith ſhould neuer faile. So that though <hi>Siluerſter</hi> the ſecond, <hi>Alexan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der</hi> the ſixth, &amp; <hi>Hildebrànd</hi> became firebrands in hell: yet all the Popes that haue bin or ſhal be, ſhal be ſaued<note place="margin">Bernard.</note> 
               <hi>hanc miſericordiam nole;</hi> I deſire no ſuch mercy at Gods hand. But <hi>ex fructibus eorum cognoſcetis eos,</hi> by their fruits (ſaith our Sauiour) you ſhall know them.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ierem.</hi> Non locus ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mines, ſed ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mines locum ſanctificant.</note> 
               <hi>Non omnes filij ſanctorum qui loca ſancta te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent:</hi> they are not all the ſonnes of Saints, nor Saints themſelues which hold the places of Saints. God oftentimes beſtoweth vpon wicked and vngodly men high titles and great places, partly to their greater condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:6976:10"/> 
               <hi>Celſae grauiore caſu decidunt turres.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Seneca. S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> mons ſubli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mis, profundior eſt tibi vallis.</note> 
               <hi>feriunt<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> ſummos fulmina montes;</hi> The migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty ſhall bee mightily tormented, and partly for the puniſhment of vngratefull people, as to <hi>Saul</hi> ouer the Iſraelites.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly, whereas the Apoſtle <hi>Iude</hi> plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth his calling; partly that his doctrine might with more attention and reuerence be receiued, and partly to comfort himſelfe in his calling; aſſuring himſelfe that hee which called him and ſent him, would bleſſe him, proſper him, and be with him; wee which are the meſſengers of God, miniſters of Chriſt, and Chriſts mouth, muſt not bee aſhamed of our calling, but boldly profeſſe, and openly plead our calling, though ſcornefully by ſcor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners of religion wee are tearmed prieſts. The Iewes thought they mocked Chriſt, when bowing their knees they cried <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Haile King of the Iewes;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Matth. 27.29.</note> againſt their wils they honoured him, for indeed hee was the King of the Iewes, and Gentiles.<note place="margin">Qui volens de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trabit famae meae, nolens ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit mercedi meae. Auguſtine.</note> So when theſe graceleſſe contemners of our glorious calling thinke to vilifie vs by tearming vs prieſts, (againſt their wils) they magnifie vs, for indeed we are the Lords prieſts to ſerue in his houſe, and attend at his table; the ſcorn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full behauiour (then) and reprochfull ſcoffes of godleſſe atheiſts, and worthleſſe miſcreants ſhall not daunt and diſcourage vs in our cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, aſſuring our ſelues, that hee which hath
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:6976:11"/> called and ſent vs will be with vs, as hee was with <hi>Moſes:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Exod. 3.12. Ierem. 1.8.</note> 
               <hi>certainely I will bee with thee,</hi> with <hi>Ieremy: Be not afraid of their faces, I will be with thee to deliuer thee;</hi> with the Diſciples: <hi>Behold I ſend you forth as lambes among wolues. He that heareth not you heareth not me, hee that receiueth not you receiueth not me,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Matth. 28.20.</note> 
               <hi>he that deſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth you deſpiſeth me; but behold I am with you alwaies vnto the end of the world.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Thirdly wheras the Apoſtle <hi>Iude</hi> doth not firſt entitle himſelfe the brother of <hi>Iames,</hi> and then the ſerua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of Ieſus Chriſt, but firſt the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uant of Ieſus Chriſt, and then the brother of <hi>Iames,</hi> we learne to eſteeme it a greater priui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, honour and dignity to be the ſeruants of Ieſus Chriſt,<note place="margin">Non refert qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus parentibus quis ortus ſit, ſi ſit virtute prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litus.</note> then to be allyed to the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt princes, potentates and perſonages in the world; for if the ſeruants of Ieſus Chriſt (though neuer ſo poore, baſe, beggerly, igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, contemptible) yet happie and bleſſed: If not the ſeruants of Ieſus Chriſt, though neuer ſo rich, noble, honorable, great in this world; yet miſerable and wretched. Witneſſe <hi>Diues</hi> and <hi>Lazarus.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Poſtridie ſum <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>atus ego quam <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>upiter.</note> 
               <hi>Aiax</hi> boaſted that hee was <hi>(à Ioue tertius)</hi> the third from <hi>Iupiter</hi>) and yet a Pagan, infidell, one that neuer knew, ſerued, truly worſhipped <hi>Iehouah</hi> the true God. <hi>Infoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liciſſimus Aiax,</hi> moſt wretched and vnhappy <hi>Aiax,</hi>
               <note place="margin">E meglio viuer <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>virtuoſa-mentè the naſcer no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilimente.</note> thy royall alliance could not keepe thee from murthering thy ſelfe and tumbling into hell. <hi>Iude</hi> profeſſeth himſelfe the ſeruant
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:6976:11"/> of Ieſus Chriſt: <hi>foeliciſſimus Iudas,</hi> moſt happy and bleſſed <hi>Iudas,</hi> thy ſeruice made thee truly bleſſed in this life; and perfectly bleſſed after this life. If then with this Apoſtle we profeſſe our ſelues, and deſire to ſhew our ſelues in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed the ſeruants of Ieſus Chriſt, we muſt doe three things:
<list>
                  <item>1. Firſt, we muſt imitate our maſters vertues.</item>
                  <item>2. Secondly, we muſt attend his pleaſure.</item>
                  <item>3. Thirdly, we muſt addict our ſelues wholly to his ſeruice.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>In our Lord and Maſter Chriſt Ieſus ſhined many excelle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t vertues, yea all vertues; loue, pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience, humility, meeknes, mildnes, mercy, cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mency, purity, piety, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,<note place="margin">Iohn 1.14.</note> the fulneſſe of grace and truth; theſe muſt ſhine in vs, loue, patience, humility, mildneſſe, meekneſſe, gentleneſſe, goodneſſe, clemency, purity, piety: elſe falſely are we called the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants of Chriſt. <hi>Chriſtiani nomen fruſtrà ille ſortitur, qui Chriſtu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> minimè imitatur, quid tibi prodeſt vocari quod non es?</hi>
               <note place="margin">De vita Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtiana.</note> In vaine (ſaith S. <hi>Auguſtine</hi>) hath hee gotten the name of a Chriſtian, which doth not imitate Chriſt; what doth it profit thee to bee called that which thou art not? To be called a Chriſtian, and not to be indeed a Chriſtian; a ſaint, and not to be a ſaint, the ſeruant of Ieſus Chriſt, and not to bee his ſeruant? If thou takeſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light to be called a Chriſtian, do thoſe things which beſeeme and belong to a Chriſtian, and
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:6976:12"/> then deſeruedly thou ſhalt bee called a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly, we muſt attend our maſters plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, and depend on his will, not appointing him either time or place, or meanes: but re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting in his gratious promiſes, and relying on his prouident care ouer vs. For, to diſtruſt the truth of his promiſes were to offend Chriſt the maſter of beleeuers with the ſinne of vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vnbeleefe: to doubt of his power to performe them, were to denie power to be in him, to whom all power is giuen both in heauen and in earth.<note place="margin">Matth. 28.18.</note> Herein then we reſt, and hereon wee muſt relie; if we want, he is our Lord and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, he can, hee will ſupply our wants. If in troubles, he is our Lord and maſter, hee can, hee will rid vs out of troubles. If hated, perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted, wrongfully impriſoned, he is our Lord and maſter, hee can, hee will deliuer vs. If in ſorrowes and heauineſſe of heart, hee is our Lord and maſter, he can, he will comfort vs: If in ſickneſſe, hee is our Lord and maſter, hee can, hee will either reſtore vs to our former health, or receiue vs into his euerlaſting king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Thirdly, we muſt addict our ſelues wholly to his ſeruice, not ſeruing any other maſter in our ſpirituall ſeruice; not the world, not the fleſh, not the diuell, not Antichriſt; Not the world, <hi>nè illecti,</hi> leſt allured with the vaine pleaſures and lying vanities thereof: not the
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:6976:12"/> fleſh, <hi>nè infecti,</hi> leſt ſtained, polluted, defiled therewith; not the diuell, <hi>nè interfecti,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <p>
                     <hi>O quàm multo dom nos habet qui vnum non habet.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>O how many maſters hath he which hat not Chriſt for his onely ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter.</p>
               </note> leſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed and deuoured by him. Not Antichriſt, <hi>nè decepti,</hi> leſt ſeduced and miſled by him. He that ſerues the fleſh ſerues his fellow: he that ſerues the world ſerues his ſeruant: hee that ſerues the diuell ſerues his enemie. Hee that ſerues Antichriſt ſerues Chriſts enemie, but he that ſerues Chriſt Ieſus, ſerues the greateſt and beſt Lord: the greateſt, as beſt able, the beſt, as moſt willing to reward his ſeruants. As then they only are actually in Ieſus Chriſt, which walke not after the fleſh but after the ſpirit;<note place="margin">Rom. 8.1.</note> ſo they onely are the ſeruants of Ieſus Chriſt, which in their ſpirituall ſeruice ſerue no maſter but Ieſus Chriſt. Hence is it that the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> proteſteth, that if in the preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Goſpell hee ſhould ſerue or pleaſe men, hee could not bee the ſeruant of Ieſus Chriſt: The reaſon is, becauſe Chriſts plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure and mens pleaſures; Chriſts doctrine and mens humours; Chriſts verity, and mens va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nities, Chriſts wiſedome and mens follies can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ſtand, cannot accord together. Turkes, Pagans, Infidels which plainely deny Chriſt, doe not ſo much derogate from Chriſt as pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane profeſſors of Chriſt. For Turks and Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gans denie Chriſt in profeſſion, Heretickes in doctrine; but prophane profeſſors in life and conuerſation.<note place="margin">Auſten.</note> 
               <hi>Tolerabilius lingua quàm vita mentitur.</hi> The lie that is made by the tongue
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:6976:13"/> is more tollerable then that which is made by the life. For when the tongue profeſſeth Chriſt, and yet the heart full of impuritie, and the life full of impietie, this is not <hi>profeſſio, ſed abnegatio Chriſti,</hi> not a profeſſing but an open denying of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>Laſtly whereas this Apoſtle doth not call himſelfe the brother of Chriſt, as elſewhere the ſcripture doth, but the ſeruant of Ieſus Chriſt, we ſee his wonderfull humilitie: he ſuppreſſeth his moſt worthy ſtocke and glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rieth not in his greateſt kinred, but contents himſelfe to bee called the ſeruant of Ieſus Chriſt. It is not ſo in theſe dayes. <hi>(Si verbis au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dacia detur)</hi> if I may ſpeake boldly and plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly it is cleane contrary:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Saluſt</hi> obiected to <hi>Tully</hi> that he was no gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman, and herefore vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy to beare office. Indeed ſaith <hi>Tully</hi> my nobi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity begins in me, and thine ends in thee.</note> for ſome, which haue neither learning, nor liuing, nor wiſedom, nor ciuility, nor honeſty, nor pietie at all, yet if they can fetch their pedegree from ſome noble or worſhipfull houſe, they boaſt there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, hold themſelues worthy of reuerence, and thinke themſelues wronged, if they be not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garded. What did the <hi>Iewes</hi> gaine, by glory<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that <hi>Abraham</hi> was their father? <hi>ſemen Abrahae ſumus, pater noſter Abraham:</hi> we are the ſeed of <hi>Abraham: Abraham</hi> is our father, when our ſauiour told them;<note place="margin">Iohn 8.44.</note> 
               <hi>vos eſtis ex patre Diabolo,</hi> you are of your father the deuill, and his works you do. Indeed they were the ſeed of <hi>Abraham</hi> with <hi>Iſmael,</hi> but not the ſonnes of <hi>Abraham</hi> with <hi>Izaak.</hi> Grant them to bee
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:6976:13"/> ſonnes, yet they were ſonnes according to the fleſh, not according to the promiſe. For,<note place="margin">Non habent hae reditatem Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triqui fidem Petri non ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bent. Ambr. d paeniten. lib. <hi>1.</hi> cap. <hi>6.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Non ſunt filij Abrahae qui non ſequuntur fidem A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brahae,</hi> they are not the ſonnes of <hi>Abraham</hi> which follow not the faithful ſteps of <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham.</hi> Outward titles (then) without inward vertues auaile vs nothing, for what ſhall it profite vs to be entitled Chriſtians, and yet liue as prophanely as infidells? to bee called the Church of God, and yet in co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uerſation re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemble the Synagogue of Satan. To be coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the children of God,<note place="margin">Qualis haberi velis, talis fias.</note> and yet ſpend our times like the ſonnes of <hi>Belial</hi> to bee reputed the ſeruants of Chriſt Ieſus, and yet ſerue the world the fleſh and the deuill? to deſcend of noble, godly parents, and yet degenerate from their noble godly wayes? God is not pleaſed with ſhadowes, but with ſubſtance: not with outward titles, but with truth in the inward parts. Therefore <hi>Theodoſius</hi> the Em<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>perour held it a more noble thing to be <hi>Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> eccleſiae,</hi> then <hi>caput imperij,</hi> A me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber of the Church then head of the Empire. If then thou wilt boaſt of thine honorable kindred, labour, ſtriue, endeuour that thou mayeſt truely glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, and ſay that God is thy father,<note place="margin">La virtu è ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gume to a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilita.</note> the Church thy mother, Chriſt Ieſus thy elder brother, this is moſt high, holy, honorable kindred. Thus much of the perſon ſaluting, his name, his calling, his kinred.</p>
            <pb n="18" facs="tcp:6976:14"/>
            <p>The perſons ſaluted are beautified with three excellent Titles.
<list>
                  <item>1. called.</item>
                  <item>2. ſanctified.</item>
                  <item>3. reſerued to Ieſus Chriſt.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>Calling is twofold.
<list>
                  <item>1. to ſome office and duty.</item>
                  <item>2. to the knowledge of God and ſaluation.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>To ſome office and dutie either priuate or publique, priuate and oeconomical; as maſters of families, artificers, husbandmen. Publique is either ciuill, or eccleſiaſticall: Ciuill is ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in peace as Magiſtrates, or in warre as militarie Gouernors. Eccleſiaſticall is either immediate by God and Chriſt, as prophets and Apoſtles, or mediate by men, as Archbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops, Biſhops, Miniſters of the word. Calling to the knowledge of God and ſaluation is ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther externall or internall: Externall is either common to all, by the inſtinct of Nature and works of creation;<note place="margin">Pſalme.</note> or not co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon to all, by the word preached. The Lord hath not dealt ſo with euery nation. Internall and effectuall is a worke of the whole Trinitie, whereby God the father, through the ſon, by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> holy Ghoſt, not onely offers grace, but giueth it to the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect. <hi>Vocantur electi, vel foris, per externam prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicationem, vel intus efficaci operatione ſperitus ſancti.</hi> The elect are called either without by the outward preaching of the word, or within by the inward effectuall operation of the holy Ghoſt. This hath two partes, the one inuite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:6976:14"/> the other admiſſion. Inuitement is when God offers remiſſion &amp; life euerlaſting to all that beleeue, &amp; this outwardly by the preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the word: and inwardly by inſpiration of heauenly deſires. Admiſſion is whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> men are entred into the kingdom of grace; &amp; this out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly, by Baptiſme, &amp; inwardly, by the ſpirit: engraffing them into Chriſt, and making them reall members of Gods kingdome. This is di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers in reſpect of time and in reſpect of place. In reſpect of time, for God calleth in diuers houres of the day, that is in diuers ages of the world, and in diuers yeares of our age: ſome before the law, as <hi>Abel, Enoch, Noah, Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham,</hi> ſome vnder the law, as <hi>Moſes, Dauid, Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſias, Iſay</hi> with other kings and Prophets: ſome after the law; as the bleſſed Apoſtles, Martyrs, Confeſſors. Some in the firſt houre, (their childhood,) as <hi>Samuel, Ieremy, Iohn Baptiſt.</hi> Some in the third houre (their youth) as Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niel, and <hi>Iohn</hi> the Euangeliſt. Some in the ſixth houre (their middle age) as <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>Andrew.</hi> Some in the eleuenth houre (their old age (as <hi>Gamaliel,</hi> and <hi>Ioſeph</hi> of <hi>Arimathea;</hi> ſome in the laſt houre of the day (the laſt hour of their life) as the theefe vpon the croſſe. In reſpect of place, for God calleth ſome from their ſhips, and ſome from their ſhops, ſome from the market, and ſome from vnder the hedges. This diuers calling at diuers times and in diuers places, intimates a caueat and a
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:6976:15"/> comfort.<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>em dicat, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eo me voca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t, quia colat <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eum: quoma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſſes ſi <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>catus n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>es? Auſten de <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>erb. Apoſt.</note> A caueat, for ſuch as are called, that they magnifie not themſelues, and vilifie o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers. A comfort for them that feele not them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues ſufficiently called, that they reſt in hope God can &amp; wil call, when, where, &amp; whom he will, either at the laſt houre with the theefe vpon the gallowes, or out of oppreſſing Egypt with the Iſraelites, or perſecuting <hi>Paul</hi> brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing out ſlaughter againſt the Saints of God.</p>
            <p>The vſes hereof are three.</p>
            <p>Firſt, ſeeing we are called of God, we muſt walke worthie of our calling; that as hee which hath called vs, is in himſelfe moſt holy; ſo ſhould we not onely begin well, but con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue in holineſſe and righteouſneſſe all the daies of our liues. For to this end hath the grace, goodneſſe, bountifulneſſe of our Lord appeared, <hi>vt abnegata omni impietate,</hi> that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nying and renouncing all impiety of life, and impurity of heart, we ſhould liue in this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent life,<note place="margin">Sobriè. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uſtè. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iè. Haec tria perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uò meditare aduerbia Pauli. Haec tria ſunt vitae regula ſancta tuae.</note> ſoberly, iuſtly, godly: Soberly to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards our ſelues, iuſtly towards others, godly towards God: becauſe, <hi>ſancta conuerſatio con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fundit inimicum, aedificat proximum, glorificat Deum.</hi> A holy life, and godly conuerſation, doth confound and ſtop the mouthes of our enemies, doth edifie and build vp our bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, doth glorifie God.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly, ſeeing we are called of God, not onely generally, but particularly (for euery one that liueth in the Church and Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:6976:15"/> ought to haue a particular calling to walke in) wee muſt ioyne the practiſe of our particular calling with the practiſe of our ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall calling. For it is not ſufficient for a man to be a Chriſtian in the congregation and in common conuerſation, vnleſſe hee ſhew him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe ſo in his particular calling. A magiſtrate muſt not onely be a Chriſtian in generall, but a Chriſtian magiſtrate in bearing the ſword. A Miniſter muſt not onely bee a Chriſtian in generall, but he muſt be a Chriſtian Miniſter in feeding the flocke, <hi>verbo praedicationis, fru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctu orationis, exemplo conuerſationis,</hi> with the word of preaching, with the fruit of prayer, with the example of holy conuerſation. A maſter of a family muſt not onely bee a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian abroad in common conuerſation, but a Chriſtian in the regiment and gouernment of his particular family. Thus muſt euery man behaue himſelfe in his particular calling. The reaſon is, becauſe the practiſe of our particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar calling ſeuered from the generall, is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing elſe but the practiſe of iniuſtice &amp; pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phaneneſſe, and our generall calling without the practiſe of ſome particular, is nothing elſe but the ſhew of godlineſſe without the power thereof.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Thirdly, ſeeing we are called not only in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly by the holy ſpirit, but outwardly by the holy word; this word muſt bee to vs dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer then thouſands of ſiluer and gold, more
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:6976:16"/> precious then the gold of <hi>Ophir,</hi> ſweeter then the hony and the hony combe. For albeit God can onely by the inward motion of his bleſſed ſpirit worke out, make ſure and perfect our ſaluation; yet it pleaſeth him in his eternall wiſedome to vſe the word as the ordinarie means of our vocation and ſaluation. As then, God giueth learning by ſtudie, wiſedome by experience, riches by trauell, and like things by like meanes; ſo he maketh perfect the cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of his Saints by the preaching of the word,<note place="margin">Cor. 2.15.</note> which is the power of God to ſaluati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. the ſauor of life vnto life.</p>
            <p>The ſecond title of honour giuen heere to the Saints is ſanctification, <hi>ſanctified of God the father.</hi> Here may it pleaſe you to obſerue two circumſtances; the one what ſanctifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is, the other whence it is. To bee ſanctifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, is to bee ſeparated, conſecrated and ſet a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part from common vſes, and reſerued to ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred and holy vſes. Thus in the law, thoſe things were called holy and ſanctified, which were taken from the common vſe of the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and ſet apart for the vſe and ſeruice of God; as the oyle, ſhewbread, firſt fruits, veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels of the tabernacle. In this ſenſe the Prieſts were called holy, becauſe they were ſeparate from the common life of men to ſerue in the tabernacle, and offer holy ſacrifices. Thus the people of Iſrael ſeparated from the reſt of the nations, were called by <hi>Moſes</hi> a ſanctified
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:6976:16"/> people to the Lord,<note place="margin">2.3.</note> by <hi>Ieremie</hi> a thing hallo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wed to the Lord. Now of them that are ſaid to be Saints, there are three ſorts,<note place="margin">Confitemur ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gati profitemur vlirò.</note> ſuch as con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe and profeſſe Chriſtian religion in word onely, but in workes deny the power thereof.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Such as not only confeſſe and profeſſe Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian religion in word, but alſo in a ciuill ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt life before men expreſſe the ſame.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Such as being choſen to true holineſſe, effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctually called, iuſtified, regenerated and truly ſanctified, doe leade their liues in holineſſe and righteouſneſſe.<note place="margin">Zanch. Miſcel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lan. lib. <hi>3.</hi> cap. <hi>1.</hi> tract. de ſanctis.</note> The firſt are ſaints nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther before God nor the Church. The ſecond are ſaints before the Church but not before God: the third are ſaints before God and the Church. Theſe are ſanctified by a threefold ſanctification. 1. Imputed vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. 2. wrought in them. 3. wrought by them.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Imputed ſanctification is when God impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth to vs the ſanctification of Chriſt,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 1.30.</note> who is made to vs wiſedome, righteouſneſſe, ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication and redemption: by this wee are ſaid to be ſanctified, when the vertue of Chriſts paſſion, the fruit of his death, the power of his reſurrection is applied to vs, and Chriſts ſanctification made ours by imputation. Ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Apoſtle ſaith,<note place="margin">Heb. 13.12.</note> that <hi>Ieſus Chriſt to the end that hee might ſanctifie his people with his owne blood, ſuffered without the gate.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Sanctification wrought within vs, is the inward change of a man iuſtified, whereby
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:6976:17"/> the image of God is reſtored in him: a change, not a <hi>non eſſe ad eſſe,</hi> from a not being to a be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, for the faculties of the ſoule were before: nor, <hi>ab eſſe ad non eſſe,</hi> from a being to a not being, for the faculties of the ſoule remaine ſtill: but <hi>ab eſſe ad eſſe,</hi> from an ill being to a good being; not aboliſhing the will, mind and affections, but rectifying and renuing them. A change of a man iuſtified; for we are iuſtified before we are ſanctified. Iuſtification is, <hi>actus indiuiduus,</hi> ſanctification is, <hi>actus diui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duus:</hi> we are iuſtified at once, we are ſanctifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by degrees: we are iuſtified when our ſins are not imputed vnto vs, wee are ſanctified when a cleane heart is created, and a right ſpi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rit renued in vs. Laſtly by this inward change the image of God conſiſting in righteouſnes and true holineſſe is reſtored within vs.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Sanctification wrought by vs is that wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by wee ſanctifie and make holy the outward works and actions of our life. This the Lord requireth, <hi>eſtote ſancti, quia ego ſanctus.</hi> Be yee holy,<note place="margin">Leuit. 11.14.</note> for I the Lord your God am holy. To this Saint <hi>Paul</hi> exhorteth. <hi>Let vs cleanſe our ſelues from all filthineſſe of the fleſh,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Cor. 7.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>and of the ſpirit, and grow vp to full holineſſe in the feare of God.</hi> Of this Saint <hi>Iohn</hi> ſpeaketh, (ſpeaking alſo of that hope which we haue of the glory to come) he which hath this hope <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,<note place="margin">1. Iohn 3.3.</note> ſanctifieth or purifieth himſelfe as hee is pure. The righteouſneſſe of iuſtification is by faith
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:6976:17"/> without workes: the righteouſneſſe of ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctification is by workes and by faith. Iuſtify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing righteouſnes is perfect, but not inherent: ſanctifying righteouſneſſe is imperfect, but inherent. Glorifying righteouſneſſe is perfect and inherent. Neuertheleſſe we muſt confeſſe that all our ſanctification is from the Lord. Sanctified (ſaith the Apoſtle) of God the father.</p>
            <p>Albeit, <hi>opera dei ad extra ſunt indiuiſa,</hi> the outward workes of God bee common to the whole trinity, and ſo wee are ſanctified by the Father, Sonne, and holy Ghoſt, yet ſanctifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is heere aſcribed to the Father as being the ground and firſt author thereof. For the Sonne ſanctifieth by meriting ſanctification, the holy Ghoſt ſanctifieth by working it, but the Father ſanctifieth both by ſending his Sonne to merit it, and alſo by giuing his holy ſpirit to worke it.</p>
            <p>The vſes are two.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Firſt, that ſeeing we are ſanctified, we muſt hereby be ſtirred vp to all holines, righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, and true ſanctification, that our names and our natures, our calling and our conuerſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion may bee correſpondent. If then wee will haue part with Chriſt, wee muſt liue after the example of Chriſt. If we will haue communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on with the ſaints on earth, we muſt be ſaints on earth. If we wil haue the company of ſaints in heauen, our conuerſation on earth muſt
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:6976:18"/> be heauenly;<note place="margin">Epheſ. 1.4.</note> partly becauſe we are choſen in Chriſt that wee ſhould bee holy and without blame before him, and partly becauſe the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly court receiueth none,<note place="margin">Reuel. 21.27.</note> but ſuch as are pure, holy, innocent.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly, ſeeing we are ſanctified, we muſt now doe the workes of our calling in a good and godly maner.<note place="margin">Nouos homines <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ouae vitae acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nes edere o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ortet.</note> To this two things are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired, holineſſe and conſtancie: holineſſe of the worker, and holineſſe of the worke. Of the worker, partly becauſe the perſon muſt firſt pleaſe God, before the worke of the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon can pleaſe him: and partly becauſe we can looke for no ſucceſſe and bleſſing vpon our labours vnleſſe we be ſanctified. Holineſſe of the worke, becauſe euen lawfull actions (vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe they be ſanctified) are ſins, as appeareth in one and the ſame action done by the Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſie &amp; the Publican; the Phariſie praied in the pride of his heart; the Publican in the humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity of his mind. To this two things are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired, the one, the word of God which gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth direction to eſchew vices, as couetouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and iniuſtice; and to practiſe vertues, as faith and loue: the other, prayer not onely for the ſupply of graces, but for a bleſſing vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the labours of our calling. The ſecond thing required in doing the works of our cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling in a good manner is conſtancie, a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant perſeuering in good duties. For it is no commendation to begin well, vnleſſe we con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:6976:18"/> in well doing. <hi>Incaſſum bonum agitur,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Libro <hi>1.</hi> medi.</note> 
               <hi>ſi ante vitae terminum deſcratur: quia fruſtrà ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lociter currit, qui priuſquam ad metas venerit, deficit:</hi> In vaine (ſaith <hi>Gregory</hi>) is good done, if a man giue ouer doing good before he die, becauſe hee runneth in vaine ſwiftly which fainteth before he come at the marke. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore all impediments and lets laid aſide, wee muſt goe on with courage and conſtancie, paſſing through good report and euil report, through ſhame and rebuke.</p>
            <p>The third title of honour giuen here to the ſaints is, that they are reſerued to Ieſus Chriſt. That is (as Saint <hi>Peter</hi> ſaith) <hi>They are kept by the power of God through faith to ſaluation.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Pet. 1.5.</note> 
               <note place="margin">Herba, Spica, Frumentum in ſpica.</note> Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold here the Apoſtles gradation: God cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth vs, hauing called vs ſanctifieth vs, hauing ſanctified vs, reſerueth vs as a ſpeciall portion, peculiar part, and chiefe treaſure to and for his ſonne Chriſt Ieſus. By this is the promiſe of God the father performed to his ſon:<note place="margin">Pſal. 2.8.</note> 
               <hi>Aske of me and I will giue thee the heathen for thine inheritance, and the vttermoſt parts of the earth for thy poſſeſſion.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Epheſ. 1.22.</note> Hence it is that Saint <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, God hath made all things ſubiect vnder his feet, <hi>and hath appointed him ouer all things to be the head to the Church.</hi> Hence is the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, honour, dignity of the ſaints and ſeruants of God, that God layeth them vp as a chiefe treaſure in the treaſurie of his Almighty po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer and watchful prouidence, reſerueth them
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:6976:19"/> to Ieſus Chriſt the true heire of the world and lord of the Church, and maketh them co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heires with him in his euerlaſting kingdome.</p>
            <p>The vſes hereof are three.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Seeing we are reſerued by God the Father to Ieſus Chriſt, we need not feare the day of death nor the day of iudgement; for in the laſt day it ſhall bee ſaid to euery one reſerued to Ieſus Chriſt; <hi>Hodie mecum eris in Paradiſo.</hi> This day ſhalt thou bee with mee in Paradiſe. And in the laſt day of the world, to them all, <hi>venite benedicti,</hi> come ye bleſſed of my Father, inherit the kingdome prepared for you. Ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they may now wiſh (with <hi>Paul</hi>) to be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolued and to be with Chriſt: ſing (with old <hi>Simeon,) Lord now letteſt thou thy ſeruant de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part in peace;</hi> and cry out (with the ſaints vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Altar) <hi>Come Lord Ieſu, come quickly.</hi> Thou which art our Lord by right of creati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, by right of redemption, by right of guber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, by right of preſeruation; Thou which art <hi>Ieſus our Sauiour,</hi> ſauing vs from the ſlaue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of ſinne, the tyranny of Satan, the torments of hell, come in glory, to crowne vs with per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect glory, come quickly, make no long ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rying.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly, ſeeing wee are reſerued by God the Father to Ieſus Chriſt, we muſt all our life long prepare our ſelues, that we may be fit to bee preſented as pure ſpouſes to our pure bridegrome; this is done partly, by betroth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:6976:19"/> our ſoules to Chriſt by ſaith, and partly by beautifying them with holy vertues and god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly qualities, that hauing our lamps full of oile, we may enter with the bridegroome into the bridechamber, where is <hi>Gaudium fine fine, ſine metu finis,</hi> Ioy without end, without feare of end.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Thirdly, ſeeing we are reſerued by God the Father to Ieſus Chriſt, wee need not feare the grace of perſeuerance. The reaſons are theſe.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Wee are as trees planted by the riuers ſide, whoſe leaues ſhall neuer fade and fall away.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Wee are as houſes built on a rocke, which cannot be ouerturned with the violent blaſts of perſecutions, or with the raging flouds of tentations.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> We are as plants planted into Chriſt Ieſus, which can neuer be pulled out: the reaſon is, becauſe we beare not the root, but the roote beareth vs.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> Wee are Chriſts ſheepe of his folde, out of whoſe hands all the powers of hell ſhall neuer be able to take vs.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> Laſtly, God hath put his feare into our hearts that wee ſhall not depart from him. <hi>Talis ac tantus erit timor meus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ier. 32.40.</note> 
               <hi>quem dabo in cor eorum, vt mihi perſeuerenter adhaereant:</hi> Such and ſo great ſhall my feare be, which I will put into their hearts that they ſhall with perſeuerance cleaue vnto me.<note place="margin">Auſten Tom. <hi>7.</hi> de bono perſeu. Cap. <hi>2.</hi>
               </note> Therefore ſaith Saint <hi>Auſten, ipſe facit perſeuerare in bono, qui
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:6976:20"/> facit bonos: qui autem cadunt &amp; pereunt, in pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſtinatorum numero non fuerunt.</hi> He maketh them to perſeuere in good, which maketh them good, but they which fall away and pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh were neuer in the number of thoſe that are predeſtinate to eternall life. Thus much of the perſons ſaluted, their vocation, ſanctifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, and reſeruation to Ieſus Chriſt.</p>
            <p>The forme of ſalutatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> followeth, wherein the Apoſtle wiſheth &amp; prayeth for three bleſſings.
<list>
                  <item>1. mercy.</item>
                  <item>2. peace.</item>
                  <item>3. loue.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>Mercy bee vnto you. Mercy in God is not paſſiue but actiue; <hi>non quoad affectum, ſed quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ad effectum,</hi> not ſuffering with vs in our wants, but ſuccouring vs in them.</p>
            <p>The mercy of God towards his creatures is fourefold:
<list>
                  <item>1. generall.</item>
                  <item>2. ſpeciall.</item>
                  <item>3. temporary.</item>
                  <item>4 ſempiternall.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> The generall mercy of God is that, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by hee ſuccoureth and ſupplieth the wants, needs and neceſſities of all his creatures on earth, as well ſenſible as reaſonable: Hence it is that he cauſeth his ſunne to ſhine as wel vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the vngodly as the godly; his raine to fall as well vpon the field of the reprobate, as vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the field of the righteous, that he powreth out his temporall benefits as well vpon the caſtawaies, as thoſe that are effectually called. For there are ſome good things which God giueth as well to the vngodly as to the godly,
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:6976:20"/> as health, wealth, riches, honour, ſtrength, beautie, comelineſſe of perſonage, wife, chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, learning, &amp;c. There are ſome good things which God giueth to the godly and not to the vngodly; as ſauing faith, ſauing grace, a new heart, a right ſpirit, peace of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, eternall life. There are ſome euill things, which God layeth vpon the godly as well as the vngodly, as weakneſſe of bodie, ſickneſſe, ſorrowes, loſſe of friends, famine, ſword, impriſonment: There are ſome euill things which God inflicteth vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the vngodly, and not vpon the godly; as intolerable horror of conſcience, incurable deſperatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, vnmeaſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable torme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts in hel. Finally, this general mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy of God feedeth the foules of the heauen, the fiſhes of the ſea, the beaſts of the field. His mercy is ouer all his workes, Pſal. 145.9.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> The ſpeciall mercy of God is that which extendeth it ſelfe onely to the elect. This ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued zealous <hi>Dauid</hi> from the bloody rage of furious <hi>Saul.</hi> This preſerued righteous <hi>Lot</hi> from the vnquenchable burning of <hi>Sodome</hi> and <hi>Gomorrah.</hi> This deliuered holy <hi>Daniel</hi> from the tearing lawes of hungry deuouring Lions, and <hi>Shadrach, Meſach</hi> and <hi>Abednago</hi> from the conſuming flames of a fiery furnace. <hi>Si dic as, ſalus mea, intelligo quia dat ſalutem:</hi>
               <note place="margin">on 58. Pſalme.</note> 
               <hi>Si dic as, refugium meum, intelligo quia confugis ad eum:</hi> If thou (ſaith <hi>Auſten</hi>) ſay, The Lord is my health and ſaluation, I vnderſtand thee, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:6976:21"/> hee giueth thee health and ſaluation. If thou ſay, the Lord is my refuge, I vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand thee, becauſe in all thy miſeries and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſities thou flieſt vnto him. If thou ſay the Lord is my ſtrength, I vnderſtand thee, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he giueth thee ſtrength. But if thou ſay, the Lord is my mercy, what is this, but that all that I am, is onely of thy mercy. God looketh vpon the reprobate as an angry iudge, with a cloudie countenance; but hee beholdeth his adopted children in Chriſt Ieſus as a mercifull father, with a gracious louing countenance. This is that bleſſing which the godly man a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue all bleſſings requireth. <hi>Lord lift thou vp the light of thy countenance vpon vs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> The temporary mercy of God is that wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by he ſpareth ſinners, and giueth them a time to repent, that they may be ſaued. Whence it is that when wee would ſlip from God, his mercy catcheth and holdeth vs faſt; When vaine pleaſures allure vs, to ſell God, and bee gone, his mercy will not ſo part with vs; When we are loſt in our ſelues, his mercy fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth vs out. When wee lie long in our ſinnes his mercy raiſeth vs vp: When we come vnto him, his mercy receiueth vs; When wee come not, his mercy draweth vs; When wee repent his mercy pardoneth vs; When wee repent not, his mercy waiteth our repentance. In tentation, his mercy ſtrengtheneth vs: In ſtrong deſpaire, his mercy relieueth vs: From
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:6976:21"/> errors his mercy reclaimeth vs: out of troubles his mercy deliuereth vs: In ſorrowes &amp; heaui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of hart his mercy comforteth vs; he that asketh obtaineth; he that ſeeketh findeth; he that knocketh,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Auſten</hi> on the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 144. Pſal.</note> hath the dore of Gods mercy opened vnto him. <hi>Dat veniam peccatori, ſpem iuſtificationis, charitatem in qua omnia bona fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cias, dabit vitam aeternam, &amp; ſocietatem An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gelorum.</hi> Gods mercy giueth pardon to thee a ſinner, hope of iuſtification, loue wherein thou maieſt doe all good, and Gods mercy will giue thee eternall life, and the company of holy Angels. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> 
            </p>
            <p>The ſempiternall mercy of God is that, which concernes our eternall ſaluation, electi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, creatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, rede<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ption, glorification. This mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy of God is <hi>ſpecioſa, ſpacioſa, praetioſa.</hi> Beauti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full in creating vs after his own image &amp; like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, bountiful in redeeming vs with the preti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous blood of his Son; and pretious in glorify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing vs in the kingdome of glory. <hi>Elegit in om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nibus, aſſumpſit ex omnibus, amauit prae omnibus.</hi> He choſe vs amongſt all, hee tooke vs out of all, he loued vs aboue all. Hence is it, that the Apoſtle ſaith, the Lord is <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,<note place="margin">Epheſ. 2.4.</note> rich in mercy. Rich in mercy, becauſe the treaſury of his mercy is neuer exhauſted, the fountaine neuer dried vp: Rich in mercy becauſe he ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ceaſeth to communicate the riches of his mercies to vs. Rich in mercy, becauſe hee par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doneth all our ſins vpon our true repentance,
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:6976:22"/> our great,<note place="margin">Maxima, media, minuta.</note> middle, ſmalleſt ſinnes. Rich in mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, becauſe hee not onely pardoneth all our ſinnes vpon our true repentance; but giueth vs repentance, and faith to beleeue the remiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of our ſinnes. Rich in mercy, becauſe hee giueth vs priuatiue grace to eſcape euils, and poſitiue, enabling vs to do good. Finally, rich in mercy, becauſe he preuenteth vs with mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy before wee ſeeke him, and followeth vs with mercy, when wee haue found him. In a word, the mercy of God ſignifieth three things. Firſt, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Vim miſerendi,</hi> a power, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility, pronenes of the diuine nature, to ſhew mercy. The ſecond <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>actum miſerendi miſerationem,</hi> the very act of ſhewing mercy; euen as a father ſheweth mercy to his chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren,<note place="margin">Pſal. 103.13.</note> ſo doth the Lord ſhew mercy to them that feare him. The third <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>effectum &amp; o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pus miſericordiae,</hi> the very effects and workes of mercy.<note place="margin">Pſal. 17.7.</note> 
               <hi>Shew thy maruellous mercies, thou that art the ſauiour of all them that put their truſt in thee. Tantas audis Dei miſericordias?</hi> Doſt thou heare ſo many and ſo great mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies of God, and doſt thou doubt of thy ſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard in this life, of thy ſaluation in the life to come? <hi>Dicat anima mea, dicat ſecura, tu domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne Deus meus, qui dicit animae meae, ego ſalus tua.</hi> Let my ſoule (ſaith <hi>Auſten</hi>) ſay boldly, ſecurely, confidently, Thou O Lord art my God, which ſaith vnto my ſoule, I am thy ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation. By this it appeareth how great a bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:6976:22"/> the Apoſtle wiſheth in wiſhing mercy. Mercy be vnto you.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> The ſecond bleſſing which the Apoſtle prayeth for is peace: Peace be vnto you. Peace is twofold, the one bad, the other good: the former an appearing peace,<note place="margin">Pax
<list>
                     <item>apparens</item>
                     <item>vera.</item>
                  </list>
               </note> the latter true and ſincere peace. Bad peace is threefold: <hi>pax in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quinata, pax ſimulata, pax inordinata:</hi> defi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, diſſembled, inordinate peace. Defiled and polluted peace, is when wicked men co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſpire, combine and band themſelues together to doe euill and miſchiefe to the good and god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. In league, either to doe all the miſchiefes, villanies, and outrages they can, hauing re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of neither friends nor foes; as robbers, rebels, traitors. <hi>Eſt daemonum legio concors,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Auſten.</note> there is an agreement among the diuels: in <hi>Mary Magdalen,</hi> of ſeuen, in an other of a whole legion. Such a diuelliſh agreement was amongſt thoſe inhumane, barbarous, bloody gunpowder traitors. <hi>Indigni vita, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>digni luce fuerunt,</hi> vnworthy of life, vnwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy of the light. <hi>Perierunt ipſi, &amp; eorum pere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>at memoria:</hi> They haue iuſtly periſhed, and let their memories vtterly periſh with them. Or elſe in league againſt the godly in ſome things, though at warres among themſelues.<note place="margin">Pſal 9.21.</note> 
               <hi>Ephraim</hi> againſt <hi>Manaſſeh, Manaſſeh</hi> againſt <hi>Ephraim,</hi> both againſt <hi>Iudah. Herod</hi> againſt <hi>Pilate, Pilate</hi> againſt <hi>Herod,</hi> both againſt Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus. The Phariſies againſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Sadduces, the Sad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duces
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:6976:23"/> againſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Phariſies, both againſt Chriſt. The Pelagians againſt the Maniches, the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niches againſt the Pelagians, both againſt true Catholikes. The Turke againſt the Pope, the Pope againſt the Turke, both againſt the truth: The Prieſts againſt the Ieſuits, the Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuits againſt the Prieſts, both againſt Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants.<note place="margin">Pſal. 71.10.</note> Theſe are like <hi>Dauids</hi> enemies, <hi>they laid waite for his ſoule, and tooke counſell toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther against him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Diſſembled and counterfeit peace, is when men pretend peace and intend miſchiefe. So <hi>Abſolom</hi> prepared a feaſt for his brother <hi>Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Sam. 13.28.</note> but cauſed him to be murthered in the midſt of the banquet. So <hi>Ioab</hi> ſpake peacea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly to <hi>Abner,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Sam. 3.27.</note> but ſlew him with his ſword. So <hi>Iudas</hi> kiſſed <hi>Ieſus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Matth. 26 49.</note> but betraied him. So the Spaniards in 88. treated of peace, but prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red themſelues to warre.<note place="margin">Mel in ore, ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ba lactis: fel in corde, fraus in factis.</note> 
               <hi>Ex fraude, fallacijs, mendacijs toti conſtare videntur:</hi> They ſeeme to be compounded of nothing elſe but frauds, deceits, diſſemblings, lyings.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Inordinate peace is when the greater and better obeyeth the leſſer and inferiour. So <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam</hi> obeyed <hi>Eue,</hi> when <hi>Eue</hi> ſhould haue o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beyed <hi>Adam.</hi> So reaſon obeyeth ſenſe, when ſenſe ſhould alwaies reaſon: ſo grace ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times yeeldeth to nature, when nature ſhould alwaies obey grace. Theſe kindes of peace (ſaith our Sauiour) I came not to bring into the world, but a ſword. <hi>Melior eſt talis pugna
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:6976:23"/> quae proximum facit Deo, quàm illa pax, quae ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parat à Deo:</hi> Better is that fight and conflict (ſaith <hi>Gregory Nazianzene</hi>) which maketh a man neere to God, then that peace which doth ſeparate a man from God. For <hi>vbi non eſt bellum ibi pax peruerſa,</hi> where this kinde of warre is not, there is peruerſe and inordinate peace.</p>
            <p>Good peace is foure fold:
<list>
                  <item>1. With God.</item>
                  <item>2. With the good Angels.</item>
                  <item>3. With our ſelues.</item>
                  <item>4. With men.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> With God, when reconciled vnto God, and iuſtified by a true ſauing faith,<note place="margin">Rom. 5 1. Philip. 1.4.</note> we haue the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour of God and fellowſhip in the Goſpell: this is properly called reconciliation wrought and brought to vs by Ieſus Chriſt, who is our peace. <hi>Pacem euangelizauit ijs qui propè,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Epheſ. 2.17.</note> 
               <hi>ijs qui procul:</hi> He preached peace to them that are neere, and to them that are a farre off.<note place="margin">A prioribus p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fidem iuſtific<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> praeſentia rem<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tuntur, futur<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> non imputab<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tur.</note> Being now reconciled to God by Chriſt, we are iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtified by faith from our former ſinnes: our preſent ſinnes are pardoned, our future for Chriſts ſake ſhall not be imputed.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> The ſecond good peace is that, which wee haue with the good Angels, who are recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciled vnto vs, becauſe we are reconciled vnto God. And therefore guard vs, ward vs, pitch their tents round about vs, and at the diſſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of ſoule and bodie carrie and conuey the ſoule to God, to glorie. God vſeth the mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrie
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:6976:24"/> of his good Angels for the good of the elect,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>on ex neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e, non ex me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>is Angeloru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> pro ſua gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> &amp; bonitate. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> totius <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iuerſi.</note> not of neceſſitie, not becauſe the Angels haue deſerued ſo great dignitie; but of his meere grace and goodnes, partly for his owne glorie, partly for the good of the Angels, part<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly for the order of the whole vniuerſall, part<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly for the greater comfort of the elect, and partly for the conſeruation and augmenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of loue betweene the godly and the good Angels:<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uche. de ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. creationis, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>3.</hi> cap. <hi>14.</hi>
               </note> that as their loue towards vs is ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and increaſed, <hi>multis, magnis, diuturnis offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cijs &amp; beneficijs;</hi> by many, great, continuall offices and benefits, ſo our loue and reuerence towards them may increaſe daily more and more.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> The third good peace is peace with our ſelues. This is three fold. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Firſt, when the will and affections renued by grace, and obedient to the minde enlightened by the ſpirit, are at peace. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> The ſecond, when grace ouercomming our corrupt affections, the minde is quieted and calmed. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> The third, when the conſcience perſwaded of remiſſion of ſinnes, ceaſeth to accuſe and doth excuſe. There is a conſcience (ſaith <hi>Bernard</hi>) that is good,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. de conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tia, ſect. <hi>2.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>1784.</hi>
               </note> but not quiet; there is a conſcience y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is quiet, but not good; there is a conſcience that is neither quiet, nor good; and there is a conſcience that is both quiet and good. This peace paſſeth all peace, all vnderſtanding, I meane all created vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding. For, <hi>Quid prodeſt ſi omnes laudent, &amp;
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:6976:24"/> conſcientia accuſat? aut poterit obeſſe ſi omnes derogent, &amp; ſola conſcientia defendat?</hi> What profit or comfort ſhall it be to thee,<note place="margin">Gregor. ſuper Ezech. hom. <hi>9.</hi>
               </note> if all men applaud thee, and thy owne conſcience ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe thee? or what ſhall it hurt and grieue thee, if al derogate from thee, and thine owne conſcience defend thee?</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> The fourth good peace is with men. This is twofold, the one ciuill, the other Chriſtian. Ciuill is when in the outward things of this life men liue quietly and peaceably together: ſuch peace was betweene <hi>Abraham</hi> and <hi>Abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>melech.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Geneſ. 21.27.</note> 
               <note place="margin">1. Sam. 27.5.6. Ioſua 9.15.</note> Such peace was betweene <hi>Dauid</hi> and <hi>Achis.</hi> Such peace was betweene <hi>Ioſua</hi> and the Gibeonites. To this peace the Apoſtle ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horteth: <hi>Follow peace with all men.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 12.18.</note> 
               <hi>If it be poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, as much as in you lieth haue peace with al me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Chriſtian peace is a ſweet harmony, mutual conſent and holy concord, among the ſaints and ſeruants of God. This <hi>Dauid</hi> commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth. <hi>O quàm bonum &amp; quàm iucundum.</hi> O how good and pleaſant a thing is it for bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren to dwell together in vnity. It is not <hi>bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num &amp; non iucundum,</hi> but <hi>bonum &amp; iucundum,</hi> not onely good, but pleaſant, not only plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant but good.<note place="margin">Bona ſed non iucunda; Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cunda ſed non bona; nec bon<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> nec iucunda; et bona et iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cunda.</note> There are ſome things which are good but not pleaſant, as <hi>Patience</hi> and <hi>Diſcipline.</hi> Some things are pleaſant, but not good, as carnall pleaſures and curioſity; ſome things are neither good nor pleaſant; as en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uie and worldly ſorrowes; and there are ſome
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:6976:25"/> things which are both good and pleaſant, as honeſtie and charitie. This peace Chriſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendeth to his Diſciples: <hi>Be at peace among your ſelues.</hi> To this S. <hi>Peter</hi> exhorteth: <hi>Be yee all of one minde, loue as brethren; be at vnitie a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong your ſelues.</hi> This peace is ſo neceſſarie and profitable to Chriſtian kingdomes and common-wealths, that without this they can not well continue. For as to euery well orde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red kingdome three things neceſſarily con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curre and are required; true pietie, honeſt diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipline, and holy concord: ſo where the laſt of theſe is wanting, the other two can hardly, can neuer bee found. Holy concord then is the ſweeteſt harmonie that euer ſounded, the ſtrongeſt bond that euer vnited politicall bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies together, the chiefeſt prop, piller and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruatiue of Common-wealths, <hi>cum alij ſunt pacem recipientes, alij retinentes, alij facientes;</hi> when ſome embrace peace, others retaine it, others make it.<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Pacati. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Patientes. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Pacifici.</note> The firſt are peaceable, the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond patient, the third peace-makers: to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure peace where it is not, and to preſerue it where it is. It is ſomewhat, with clemencie to ſpare and forbeare our inferiours, more with curteſie to entertaine our equals, moſt with humilitie to ſubmit our ſelues to our ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periours. It is ſomewhat, not to moleſt others in our deeds; more, not to traduce our neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour with our tongues, moſt to auoid all oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſions of doing either. It is ſomewhat not to
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:6976:25"/> publiſh the defects and infirmities of others: more, not to extenuate their gifts and good parts; moſt, to grieue at their defects, and be glad of their gifts and graces.<note place="margin">Nemini nocet, non reddit ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>la pro malis, reddit bona pro malis.</note> Therefore ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred peace hurteth no man, rendereth not euill for euill, rendereth good for euill. It maketh weake things ſtrong, poore things rich, ſmall things great; <hi>Dulce nomen pacis, res ipſa tum iucunda, tum ſalutaris.</hi> The very name of peace is ſweet and comfortable, the fruit and effect thereof pleaſant and profitable. <hi>Innumeris po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tior triumphis:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gloria in ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>celſis Deo, in terra pax, in homines be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neuolentia.</note> more to be deſired then innu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merable triumphs. This bleſſed peace is the language of heauen, the Angels brought it fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> heauen. <hi>Glory in the higheſt heauens to God, in earth peace, towards men good wil.</hi> This is the legacy which Chriſt bequeathed to his Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples. <hi>Pace<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> mea<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> do vobis:</hi> My peace I giue vnto you: my peace I leaue with you. This was the vſuall ſalutation of the Iewes <hi>Shenim vhenim: Pax vobis,</hi> Peace be vnto you. This is one of thoſe ſpeciall bleſſings which all the Apoſtles in al their ſalutatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s pray for. <hi>Grace be with you and peace. Tale bonum,</hi> (ſaith <hi>Auſten) eſt bonum pacis, vt in rebus creatis nil gratioſius ſoleat au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diri, nil delectabilius concupiſci, nil vtilius poſſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ri.</hi> Such &amp; ſo great a good is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> good of peace, that among all the things created, nothing is heard of more acceptable, nothing deſired with more delight, nothing poſſeſſed w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> more profit. Which thing our Sauiour well conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering,
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:6976:26"/>
               <note place="margin">Matth. 5.9.</note> pronounceth the peace-makers bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, for they ſhall bee called the children of God. <hi>Si Dei vocantur filij qui pacem faciunt, procul dubio, ſatanae ſunt filij qui pacem confun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dunt:</hi> If they bee called the children of God (ſaith <hi>Gregory</hi>) which make peace, doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe they are the children of the diuell which diſturbe and deſtroy peace. Seeing then that God is the God of peace, Chriſt the prince of peace, the Angels the meſſengers of peace, the Miniſters the preachers of peace, the Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates defenders of peace; the peace-makers bleſſed, and the children of the God of peace: let vs haue peace amongſt our ſelues, and pray without ceaſing for the continuance of the peace of Ieruſalem, the peace of Great Brit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine. <hi>Let them proſper</hi> (ſurely they ſhall proſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per) <hi>that wiſh it, loue it, keepe it.</hi> By this we ſee in ſome ſort, how great a bleſſing the Apoſtle wiſheth in wiſhing peace. <hi>Peace be vnto you.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The third and laſt bleſſing which the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle heere prayeth for, is Loue: <hi>Loue bee vnto you.</hi> Loue is threefold, the firſt wherewith God loueth vs: the ſecond wherwith we loue God: the third whetewith we loue one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. In the loue wherewith God loueth vs, three things are implied: <hi>aeterna beneuolentia, actualis beneficentia, paterna complacentia.</hi> The firſt is eternal good will, and the eternal good purpoſe of God towards the elect to ſhew mercy on them, doe good vnto them, ſaue
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:6976:26"/> and glorifie them: God (ſaith the Apoſtle) hath ſaued and called vs, with an holy calling,<note place="margin">2. Tim. 1.9.</note> not according to our workes, but according to his owne purpoſe and grace, which was gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen to vs through Ieſus Chriſt before the world was. The ſecond is actuall beneficence and this either temporary, <hi>ſuſtentando, regen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do, conſeruando:</hi> by ſuſtaining, ruling, preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing vs: or ſempiternall, <hi>Gloriam dando,</hi> In giuing vs eternall glory. <hi>I haue ſworne by my holineſſe I will not faile Dauid my ſeruant, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in life nor in death. Magnum eſt loqui do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minum, maius iurare:</hi> It is a great thing that the Lord vouchſafeth to ſpeake, a greater that he ſweareth. The third is fatherly approuing, liking, delighting in the elect; that as wee take pleaſure in God to be our father, ſo doth God take pleaſure in vs, to bee his children.<note place="margin">Ier. 32.41.</note> 
               <hi>Gaudebo de ipſis, benefaciendo ipſis:</hi> I will de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light in them to doe them good. This loue of God towards vs is gratuitall, vnmeaſurable, immutable.</p>
            <p>Gratuitall and free, partly becauſe it flow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth onely from his grace and goodneſſe, and partly becauſe he loueth vs, not for his good, but for our good.</p>
            <p>Vnmeaſurable, for God ſo loued the world, that he gaue his only begotten Son to ſaue the world: greater loue could not the father ſhew then to ſend his Son out of his owne boſome, greater loue could not the Sonne ſhew then
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:6976:27"/> to die for his enemies.</p>
            <p>Immutable and vnconſtant, for whom hee loueth, he loueth to the end, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>: <hi>The gifts of God are without repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance;</hi> as loue, grace, faith, vocation, Iuſtifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, ſanctification and the like.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> The ſecond loue is that wherewith we loue God: the cauſe of this loue is twofold, pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mary, ſecundary. Primary is God himſelfe, working in vs both the will and the deed, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, euen of his owne good pleaſure: <hi>Cauſa diligendi Deum,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Bernard.</note> 
               <hi>Deus eſt; modus ſine mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do:</hi> The cauſe that we loue God is God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, the meaſure without meaſure. Seconda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry cauſes of our loue towards God are foure. the firſt is becauſe God is in himſelfe the fountaine of all goodneſſe of all good things: <hi>ſummum &amp; ſupremum bonum,</hi> the chiefeſt and the greateſt good. <hi>Inuenito ſi potes aliquid pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioſius Deo, &amp; dabitur tibi:</hi> find out if thou canſt any thing more excellent, goodly, glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious, pretious then God himſelfe, and it ſhall be giuen vnto thee. <hi>Pulchrum caelum, pulchra terra, ſed pulchrior ille qui fecit illa:</hi> Goodly, glorious, beautifull is the heauen, ſo is the earth, but hee is much more goodly and glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious which made them both. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> The ſecond is becauſe he loueth vs firſt. <hi>Inuenimus eum, ſed non praeuenimus:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Deus prior in amore, poſteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>or in odio.</note> We ſought him, but hee firſt ſought vs; we found him, but hee firſt found vs; we came vnto him, but hee firſt came vnto
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:6976:27"/> vs; we loued him, but hee firſt loued vs. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> The third cauſe is becauſe of the innumerable be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefits which hee hath and daily doth powre out vpon vs, <hi>Communia, ſpecialia, ſingularia:</hi> Common to all creatures, ſpeciall to men, ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular and peculiar to good men. <hi>Totum mun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum dedit,</hi> hee hath giuen vs the whole world to be vſed by all. <hi>Vnicum ſilium dedit,</hi> he hath giuen vs his onely Sonne to be beleeued in by all. <hi>Spiritum ſanctum dedit,</hi> hee hath giuen vs his holy ſpirit to be receiued by all. <hi>Quid ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ius, quid melius daret?</hi> What ſhould hee giue greater or better? Howbeit we muſt not loue God, onely for temporall good things, for ſuch loue is reprochfull and iniurious to God: The reaſon is; <hi>Propter quod vnum quodque a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matur, illud ipſum magis amatur:</hi> If wee loue God for temporall things only, we loue them more then God. For, <hi>ceſſante beneficio, ceſſat amor:</hi> If God ceaſe to be good to vs, wee will ceaſe to loue him. <hi>Mali</hi> (ſaith <hi>Auſten) v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuntur Deo, vt fruantur mundo:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Vtimur mundo fruimur Deo.</note> 
               <hi>Boni vtuntur mundo vt fruantur Deo:</hi> The wicked and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godly vſe God, that they may enioy the world: the good and godly vſe the world, that they may enioy God. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> The fourth cauſe why we loue God, is, becauſe he hath promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed and prepared for vs ſuch good, great, glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious things; euen ſuch as neither eye hath ſeene, nor eare heard, nor the tongue of man able to expreſſe. <hi>Totus homo implebitur gaudio:</hi>
               <pb n="46" facs="tcp:6976:28"/> The whole man ſhall bee filled with ioy, and for euer freed from iniquitie, neceſſity, cala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity, mortality; enioying ſecure quietneſſe, quiet ioyfulneſſe, ioyfull bleſſednes, bleſſed euerlaſtingneſſe, and euerlaſting happineſſe. <hi>Non de his quae condidit ſed de ſeipſo:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Auſten.</note> Not of theſe things which God hath made, but of himſelfe. The maner of our loue towards God is ſet downe by our Sauiour in the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell of S. <hi>Matthew:</hi>
               <note place="margin">cap. 22. 37.</note> 
               <hi>Thou ſhalt loue the Lord thy God with all thine heart, with all thy ſoule, andd with all thy mind. With all thine heart,</hi> that is feruently; <hi>with all thy ſoule,</hi> that is, wiſely; <hi>with all thy mind,</hi> that is, conſtantly. <hi>Peter lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued Chriſt</hi> feruently. <hi>Though all men bee offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded at thee, yet will I neuer bee offended:</hi> not wiſely: <hi>Maſter pittie thy ſelfe:</hi> not conſtantly: <hi>Non noui hominem:</hi> I know not the man. But after Chriſt had looked backe vpon him hee loued Chriſt feruently, wiſely, conſtantly: For the loue of his heart ſo inflamed his zeale, the knowledge of his ſoule ſo guided it, and the conſtancy of his mind ſo confirmed it,<note place="margin">Euſeb. lib. <hi>2.</hi> Cap. <hi>25.</hi>
               </note> that without feare of the croſſe hee was crucified for his Maſter Chriſt.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> The third loue is that, wherewith we loue one another: Albeit I truſt I may ſay as <hi>Paul</hi> wrote to the Theſſalonians:<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Theſ. 4, 9.</note> 
               <hi>Concerning bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therly loue I need not ſpeake vnto you, for ye your ſelues are already taught of God to loue one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</hi> Yet the loue of Chriſt conſtraineth mee
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:6976:28"/> to entreat you that your loue one towards an other may encreaſe more and more.</p>
            <p>This loue is commanded by our Sauiour: <hi>Thou ſhalt loue thy neighbour as thy ſelfe:</hi> not preſcribing the quantity but the quality of our loue; that as we loue our ſelues truly,<note place="margin">Omnia bona nobis cupimus, quaerimus, ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctamur: om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia mala fugi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus, cauemus repellimus.</note> ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerely, continually; ſo ſhould wee loue our neighbours truely, ſincerely, continually. Not that we ſhould loue all alike: for as wee muſt doe good to all, but eſpecially to them that are of the houſhold of Faith; ſo muſt we loue all, but ſpecially them that loue God. <hi>Melio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ri maior affectus, indigentiori, maior effectus tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buendus:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Melius eſt ama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re quàm amari.</note> To the better we muſt beare greater affection, to the poorer we muſt yeeld greater releefe: Nor commanding vs to loue none more then our ſelues, for in ſome caſes we are bound to loue another more then our ſelues: as the ſubiect is bound to loue his Soueraigne more then himſelfe, being an excellent inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of much good to the Church and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth. So the Galathians louing <hi>Paul</hi> more then themſelues, would haue pulled out their eies to haue giuen them to <hi>Paul,</hi> becauſe hee was the trumpet of Gods glory and ſo worthy an inſtrument of Gods grace.</p>
            <p>This loue wherewith wee loue one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, our Sauiour commendeth to his Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples as a ſure badge, whereby they ſhall be di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſhed from others, and knowne to bee his Diſciples. <hi>By this ſhall men know that yee
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:6976:29"/> are my Diſciples, if ye loue one another.</hi> To this Saint <hi>Peter</hi> exhorteth: <hi>Aboue all things haue feruent loue among your ſelues.</hi> To this S. <hi>Iohn</hi> exhorteth: <hi>Let vs not loue in word and tongue, but in deed and in truth.</hi> To this Saint <hi>Paul</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horteth: <hi>Be yee followers of God, as deare chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, and walke in loue.</hi> And in the former Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle to the Corinthians the 13. chapter, rec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>koning vp diuers excellent gifts, perempto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily auoucheth, that without loue they are all as nothing: where alſo ſetting downe the properties of loue amongſt the reſt, as not the leaſt, ſaith that loue ſuffereth all things: <hi>pro fratribus,</hi> enduring any coſt, labour, trauell for their good; <hi>propter fratres,</hi> bearing all croſſes, afflictions, perſecutions for their ſakes: <hi>à fratribus,</hi> ſuffering wrongs, and putting vp iniuries at their hands.</p>
            <p>The reaſons why we ſhould loue one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther are chiefly theſe:</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Becauſe there is nothing more naturall, then that man ſhould loue man.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Man cannot liue alone without man. <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo homini Deus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Man is the moſt excellent creature of God vnder the heauens.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> God loueth all his creatures, eſpecially man, moſt eſpecially good men.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> God commandeth vs to loue one another: whoſe commandement not to obey, <hi>Nefas eſt,</hi> It is a wicked rebellious thing.</p>
            <pb n="49" facs="tcp:6976:29"/>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> All godly men are members of the ſame myſticall body.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="7"/> Theſe haue all one Lord, one Faith, one Hope, one Baptiſme, one Saluation, and ſhall haue all one glory in heauen, eſſential, though not accidentall. Hee is then vnworthy the name of a man which with <hi>Tymon</hi> hateth man. He is vnworthie the name of a Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an an which with <hi>Iulian</hi> perſecuteth a Chriſtian: What perſwaſion more effectuall can I vſe, then that of the Apoſtle? What example more excellent can you follow then that of our Sauiour? Colloſſians the third chapter, the twelfth and thirteenth verſes: <hi>vt ſancti, electi, dilecti:</hi> As the ſaints of God, elect of God, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loued of God; if you haue any part in theſe graces, <hi>election, ſanctification, and the loue of God, Put on the bowels of mercy, kindneſſe, hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleneſſe of mind, meekenes, long ſuffering, forbea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring one another, and forgiuing one another, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen as Chriſt freely and bountifully forgaue you, euen ſo doe yee.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Laſtly, the Apoſtle wiſheth an encreaſe of loue, <hi>Loue bee multiplyed vnto you.</hi> Becauſe loue is the fulfilling of the law, the badge of Chriſt his Diſciples, the bond of perfection, the bond of the Church, the bond of the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth, the bond of all good ſocieties: it ioyneth God vnto man, man vnto God, and man to man. It enuieth not, diſdaineth not, ſeeketh not her owne, thinketh not euill, but
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:6976:30"/> ſuffereth long, ſuffereth all things, endureth all things, couereth the multitude of ſinnes and offences: <hi>non expiando, non veniam pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merendo, ſed fraternè condonando; non vindi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cando, non diffamando:</hi> Not by purging or ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfying for ſinnes, not by deſeruing pardon, and binding God to forgiue ſinnes, but by brotherly forgiuing treſpaſſes, not reuenging our ſelues, not defaming others. <hi>Per amo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rem Dei, amor proximi gignitur; per amorem proximi, amor Dei nutritur.</hi> By louing of God our loue towards our neighbour is bred in vs, by louing our neighbour, our loue to-towards God is nouriſhed in vs. <hi>Qui proxi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mum amare negligit, Deum diligere neſcit.</hi> Hee that neglecteth to loue his neighbour, doth not yet know how to loue God: For,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iligi no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> poteſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eus ſine proxi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o: nec proxi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>us ſine Deo. Auguſtin. de <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uitat. Dei. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>b. <hi>14.</hi> cap. <hi>7.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tas eſt motus animi ad fruendum Deo propter ip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſum, &amp; ſe atque proximo propter Deum.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I conclude with the bleſſed prayer of the bleſſed Apoſtle: <hi>Mercie, peace and loue bee vnto you:</hi> Mercy from God the Father, the Father of mercies; Peace from God the Son the Prince of peace; Loue from God the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Ghoſt, the loue of the Father and the Sonne. Mercy the fountaine of ſaluation, Peace the fruit of mercie, Loue the fruit of peace. Mercy vnto you releaſing your ſinnes; Peace vnto you quieting your con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences; Loue vnto you, ioyning you vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to God, and one vnto another. Now the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:6976:30"/> God of Mercy, Peace and Loue giue you mercy, peace and loue. To whom bee aſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed all glory, honour, power, wiſedome, might and maieſty, now and for euer more. Amen.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
